Finding Aid for Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances records, 1973-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances records 1973-1999, 1989-1998
Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances.
7 linear feet
03107 Bn 2
Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances (MCATS) was a grassroots environmental organization that was formed in response to a proposed hazardous waste disposal facility in Augusta Township, Michigan. MCATS raised awareness in the surrounding communities about the dangers against such a facility, through technical research, meetings, press releases and various other activities. The records reflect MCATS’ active opposition against the proposed hazardous waste facility.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of MCATS (donor no. 9312 ) and came through Chairman Rodney Hill in March 2003. Periodical additions have been received.
Additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances (MCATS) was founded in Milan, Michigan in 1989 as a group of concerned citizens actively opposed to a proposed hazardous waste disposal facility in Augusta Township, Michigan.
MCATS originally stood for Milan Citizens Against Toxic Substances, but as their influence and membership grew, they changed their name to Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances. They believed that their concerns about hazardous waste affected not just a community, but the entire state of Michigan.
MCATS' primary focus was to defeat a proposal by Envotech, a company located in Ypsilanti, Michigan to build a hazardous waste disposal facility on top of the old Arkona Road Landfill. Envotech also went by the names of Michigan/Wayne Disposal INC., Augusta Development Corp., and EQ. In 1987, the company revealed to the public that it planned to treat hazardous waste at the Arkona Road Landfill site by burning it in an incinerator, burying it in a landfill, and injecting the leachate into two deep wells. The facility planned to handle about 400,000 tons of hazardous waste annually, incinerating 40,000-50,000 tons each year.
MCATS was organized into several committees, each with a specific function. The committees included technical research, government affairs, media/public relations, membership, and events. The technical research committee found scientific facts to build a persuasive case against the Envotech proposal. The media/public relations committee sent press releases to small local newspapers of their events and research. These activities spread MCATS' message and found them wide spread support.
In 1992, Envotech began to apply for hazardous waste permits. MCATS looked ahead to a public hearing on Envotech's application and by raising awareness in the surrounding communities, they persuaded more than 4,000 people to attend the hearing.
MCATS found more ways for their message to be heard. MCATS members ran for Milan City Council and won three seats. This allowed MCATS to form alliances with other local governments to oppose the proposed facility. A unique solution was an inter-local agreement known as AMY, which united the city governments and residents of Augusta Township, Milan, and York Township into one negotiating power. This alliance could commit one million dollars to pay for technical consultants and legal help.
In 1998, Envotech (now known as EQ) withdrew its construction application for the proposed facility in Augusta Township.
The records of Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances relate to its activities as a grassroots environmental organization. The material documents their active opposition to the proposed hazardous waste disposal facility on top of the Arkona Road Landfill. The bulk of the record group dates from the creation of MCATS in 1989 to 1998 when plans for the facility were withdrawn.
Subjects:
Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances.; Augusta (Mich.: Township); Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Hazardous waste sites--Michigan--Augusta (Mich.: Township); Waste disposal sites--Michigan--Augusta (Mich.: Township)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Citizens Against Toxic Substances.; Augusta (Mich.: Township); Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Demonstrations--Michigan.; Waste disposal facilities--Michigan--Augusta (Mich.: Township)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Organizational Materials
  The first series, Organizational Materials, contains files relating to MCATS operating structure, documenting the work of various committees. Included are meeting agendas and minutes, mailings, newsletters, and flyers.
  - MCATS General Organizational Materials 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - MCATS Education and Research Foundation (ERF) 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee Agendas and Minutes
    - 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - General Membership Agendas and Minutes
    - 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Media/Public Relations Committee 1993 (Box 1)
  - Finance Committee 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Technical Research Committee Agendas 1993-1997 (Box 1)
  - How to Organize Citizens' Group Informational Literature (Box 1)
  - Letter Writing Information 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - MCATS Flyers and Mailings 1989-1995 (Box 1)
  - MCATS Newsletters 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Radisson Hotel Meeting September 28, 1992 (Box 1)
  - AMY Agreement 1994 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The second series, Correspondence, contains correspondence within MCATS as well as letters and communication between MCATS, other environmentally focused groups, Michigan Department of Natural Resources, EPA, government officials, Envotech, and other agencies and committees, as well as press releases. The correspondence series largely documents communication concerning the proposed hazardous waste disposal facility.
  - Correspondence between Greenpeace and MCATS 1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence involving other concerned organizations 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Major TV Media 1992 (Box 1)
  - Letters to the Editor 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - Legal Correspondence with MCATS
    - Legal Correspondence with John W. Voelpel (Envotech's Legal Council) 1992 (Box 1)
    - Rogers and Twanmoh Law Offices 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Sotiroff, Abramczyk and Raus Law Offices 1992 (Box 1)
    - Dykema Gossett Law Offices 1992-1996 (Box 1)
    - Wachler and Kopson Law Offices 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Assorted Legal Correspondence concerning Arkona Road Landfill (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Legal Correspondence 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with EPA
    - MCATS 1991-1996 (Box 2)
    - Envotech 1991-1994 (Box 2)
    - Elected Officials 1991-1993 (Box 2)
    - Surrounding townships (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to EPA concerning Arkona Road Landfill (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with MDNR
    - MCATS 1991-1999 (Box 2)
    - Envotech 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - Elected Officials 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with MCATS
    - Envotech 1991-1994 (Box 2)
    - Government Officials 1989-1995 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence within MCATS (Box 2)
  - MCATS thank you letters 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence between Envotech and Surrounding Townships (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Historic Preservation Office correspondence 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County correspondence 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Hazardous Waste Policy Committee correspondence 1990 (Box 2)
  - Press Releases
    - State of Michigan 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - MCATS 1990-1995 (Box 2)
    - Envotech (Box 2)
    - EPA 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - MDNR 1991-1993 (Box 2)
- Technical and Legal Research on Arkona Road Landfill Site, Envotech, and Deep Waste Injection Wells
  The third series, Technical and Legal Research on Arkona Road Landfill Site, Envotech, and Deep Waste Injection Wells, contains information and research on deep waste injection wells by MCATS and the EPA, various site maps and diagrams, technical investigations and analysis of the Arkona Road site, reports by expert witness Donald J. Stierman, assorted depositions, testimony and statements, and the records of environmental consulting firms involved in the case. Also included are copies of Envotech's permit applications for the facility and their research on the Arkona Road Landfill site.
  - MCATS Research on Deep Injection Waste Wells 1993 (Box 2)
  - Envotech, Act 64 Permit Application May 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Envotech Application for Drilling Deep Injection Waste Wells
    - September 1991 (Box 3)
    - April 1994 (Box 3)
    - Appendices (Box 3)
    - May 1995 (Box 3)
  - Assorted Permit Documents 1992-1996 (Box 3)
  - Envotech Study on Environmental Assessment of Arkona Road Landfill March 1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Envotech Study on Human Health Risk Assessment of Arkona Road Landfill March 1992 (Box 3)
  - Notes on Envotech Health Risk Assessment 1993 (Box 3)
  - Capacity and Siting Issues 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Envotech Compliance History August 2, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Augusta Township Residents Affidavits 1996, 1998 (Box 4)
  - MCATS Members Research on Envotech Landfill 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Topographic Site Maps (Box 4)
  - Assorted Maps and Diagrams (Box 4)
  - Michigan Department of Natural Resources and USEPA Site Inspection Report July 8, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Site Review Board 1988 (Box 4)
  - Technical Research Committee Weather Station Reports 1994-1996 (Box 4)
  - Economic Impact, Property Values for Milan/Augusta Township Homes 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Remedial Action Plan 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Remediation Plan for Arkona Road Landfill Information Packet 1992 (Box 4)
  - Arkona Road Landfill Augusta Township Toxic Waste Facility Information Packet March 13, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Envotech Environmental Impact Study on Arkona Road Landfill 1992 (Box 4)
  - Hazardous Waste Deep Injection Well Information 1991, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Site Inspections/ Soil and Groundwater Monitoring Data of Arkona Road Landfill April 1, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Water Analysis 1988-1991 (Box 4)
  - Hazardous Waste Landfills Information 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Augusta Township Hazardous Waste Site, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - MCATS Slide Show and Script January 29, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Laws
    - Hazardous Waste Management Act (Box 4)
    - SB-728 (audit privilege) (Box 4)
  - EPA Review of Envotech Permit February 21, 1992 (Box 4)
  - EPA Fact Sheets 1990, 1994, 1996, 1997 (Box 4)
  - MCATS ARL Fact Sheets 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Envotech Literature 1989, 1991, 1992, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Envotech Education Center 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Waste Management 1990-1993 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Arkona Road Landfill reports 1973-1993 (Box 5)
  - General Interest reports 1989-1994 (Box 5)
  - Federal Corrections Facility 1991-1993 (Box 5)
  - Ford Motor Company 1973-1993 (Box 5)
  - Reports of Expert Witness Donald J. Stierman (Box 5)
  - Environmental Consultants
    - Woodward-Clyde 1992 (Box 5)
    - Tellus Institute 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Firms 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Depositions 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - Assorted Testimony and Statements 1994 (Box 5)
- Opposition Meetings and Resolutions
  The fourth series, Opposition Meetings and Resolutions, contains records related to different organizations' opposition to Envotech's plan. Included are records related to the environmental appeals board, public hearings, comments on public hearings and responses to said comments, petitions and resolutions by MCATS and the city of Milan
  - Environmental Appeals Board (Box 5)
  - EPA Public Notices 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - EPA and MDNR Public Hearings 1992-1996 (Box 5)
  - Public Hearing on Proposed Hazardous-Waste Injection Wells August 1994 (Box 5)
  - EPA Hearing Comments about Arkona Landfill 1994 (Box 5)
  - Assorted Written Comments Regarding Public Hearings 1992-1994 (Box 5)
  - EPA and MDNR Responses to Public Comments 1991-1995 (Box 5)
  - Southeastern Michigan Initiative (SEMI) Organization Information (Box 5)
  - MCATS Opposition to proposed facility 1993 (Box 5)
  - MCATS Petition to USEPA, Revoking Envotech Permit May 8, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Resolutions Passed by Various Townships against Arkona Facility 1987, 1992 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The fifth series, Photographs, contain photos of the Arkona Road Landfill site during various stages. It also contains a folder featuring photos of select MCATS members.
  - Aerial Photos of Arkona Road Landfill Site 1979, 1991, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Photos of Arkona Road Runoff into Marten Marietta Quarry 1989 (Box 5)
  - Photos of MCATS Members (Box 5)
  - Photos of Arkona Road Landfill after Remedial Action Plan Cap Installation September 29, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Photos of Arkona Road Landfill prior to Cap Installation September 13, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Photos of Leak at Arkona Road Landfill June 1994 (Box 5)
  - Photos of Arkona Road Landfill 1994 (Box 5)
  - Photos of Envotech Site in Augusta Township September 10, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Photos of Arkona Road Landfill Remedial Action Plan August 1996 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Photos of Arkona Road Landfill (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Photos (Box 5)
- Newspaper, Magazine and Journal Articles
  The sixth series, Newspaper, Magazine, and Journal Articles, contains articles from a number of periodicals concerning, and of interest to, MCATS and the Arkona Landfill. Included are newspaper clippings about MCATS as an organization, the Arkona Landfill, MCATS' opposition to Colonial's Inc a Milan-based auto parts plant, Envotech and their subsidiaries, the EPA and MDNR, the surrounding communities, various public hearings, Governor John Engler, and other cases similar to the proposed facility at Arkona Road.
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Assorted newspaper clippings 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
    - MCATS 1989-1995, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
    - Arkona Landfill 1977-1979, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Colonial's Inc. Milan Auto Parts Plant (Box 6)
    - Envotech/EQ and Subsidiaries 1991-1996 (Box 6)
    - Envotech Public Relations Video Tape 1992 (Box 6)
    - Leachate 1992-1995 (Box 6)
    - EPA/DNR 1992-1996 (Box 6)
    - Surrounding Communities 1991-1996 (Box 6)
    - Public Hearings 1991-1996 (Box 6)
    - Governor Engler 1991-1993 (Box 6)
    - Similar Cases 1992-1996 (Box 6)
  - Magazine and Journal Clippings
    - Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety 1991-1994 (Box 6)
    - Environmental Health Perspectives 1991-1994 (Box 6)
    - Assorted Articles (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Mounted Articles and Emails 1995 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper Articles from Milan Area Leader, Milan Gazette and other local newspapers, 1989-1998, 13 folders (Box 7)